Judson Memorial Church Oral History Archive 2008 MSS.232
Fales Library and Special Collections
Judson Memorial Church Oral History Archive
2008
Fales Library and Special Collections
Judson Memorial Church (New York, N.Y.)
Steinberg, Joanna
MSS.232
2 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 3 other containers
32 Gigabytes in 1 flash drive
The Judson Memorial Church Oral History Archive, documents an oral history project conducted by New York University graduate students in Professor Rachel Bernstein's Fall 2008 Oral History class, in conjunction with the Oridnary People, Extraordinary Lives Oral History Project. The interviewees were selected from a list developed by the Judson Church Oral History Committee and Judson historian Ed Powers and include former pastor Howard Moody and several prominent activists and artists that were involved with Judson Memorial Church programs. The oral history interviews concentrate on activities at Judson from roughly the 1950s to the 1970s, although some material falls outside this time period. The items in the collection include administrative documents associated with the project, student papers and presentations, and recordings of the oral history interviews. Additionally in 2010, one of the former students, Johanna Steinberg, interviewed more people, adding those recordings to this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Judson Memorial Church Oral History Archive was acquired from New York University Professor Rachel Bernstein in 2009 after completion of the Oral History course. The accession number associated with this gift is 2009.232.
An accretion to the collection was donated by former Bernstein student, Joanna Steinberg, in July 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2019.011.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged alphabetically by either student or interviewee name. The collection is organized into four series, two of which have been further divided into subseries. The series and subseries arrangement of the collection is as follows:
Series I: Administrative Papers
Series II: Student-Produced Material
Subseries A: Fieldwork Analysis Papers
Subseries B: Student Presentations
Subseries C: Student Presentations CDs/DVDs
Series III: Oral History Interview Audio Discs
Subseries A: Audio - Access Copies
Subseries B: Audio - Originals
Series IV: 2010 Oral History Interviews
Historical Note
In 1838, a small group in Greenwich Village, dissatisfied with local churches, founded the Berean Church on the corner of Bedford and Downing Streets. Fifty years later, under the direction of Rev. Edward Judson (1844-1914), a new church was built and named Judson Memorial Church in memoriam to Edward's father Adoniram Judson (1788-1850), the first missionary to Burma. Edward Judson chose as the new location of his church the south side of Washington Square Park, because he wanted to reach out to the neighboring Italian community. His goal was not to convert, but to help supply this community, and any other community in need, with the necessary tools to become successful and independent.
Edward Judson's mission for the Judson Memorial Church was to create a ministry devoted to social outreach, which would meet the needs of the city and of its growing immigrant population. Some of the social service programs developed during Rev. Judson's tenure included a health center, an employment service, sewing and cooking classes, a community woodpile, and the delivery of fresh milk from New Jersey farms.
Judson Church's mission of social outreach continued throughout the years following Edward Judson's ministry. Beginning in the 1950's under the leadership of the Rev. Robert Spike and continuing under Rev. Howard Moody, Judson Memorial Church established programs designed to help those in need despite the controversial or sometimes, unpopular nature of that help. The church, for example, established local networks to aid women who needed abortions, housed and cared for drug addicts and runaway teens, established a Professional Women's Clinic for women engaged in prostitution, and helped provide medical resources for people with AIDS to name only a few of it's progressive programs.
The Judson Memorial Church supported a radical arts ministry. The groundwork for involvement in the arts had been laid by Edward Judson's gospel sings and moving picture shows during the early years of the church. However, the Judson Arts Ministry did not fully take shape until the late 1950's when church members polled local artists to determine how the church could best assist the arts community. The results of this inquiry indicated that artists needed space in which to create and show their work. The Judson Memorial Church responded by making the space of the church available to artists for art exhibitions, rehearsals, and performances. The church also assured that this space was to be a place where these artists could have the freedom to experiment in their work without fear of censorship.
In 1957, the Judson Memorial Church offered gallery space to Claes Oldenburg, Jim Dine, and Robert Rauschenberg, who were then unknown artists. In 1959, the Judson Gallery showed work by Pop artists, Tom Wesselman, Daniel Spoerri, and Red Grooms. The Judson Gallery became the first home to the "happenings" movement of the 1960's. Hosted by the Judson Group, these "happenings" included Ray Gun Spex and Jim Dines' presentation of an environment called Apple Shrines.
In 1959, the Judson Literary Quarterly, Exodus, was published under the aegis of the Judson Studio. This anthology of poetry edited by Howard Hart and sold in local bookstores, included poems by William Godden, Robert Hanlon, and John Williams. Volumes I, II, and II of Exodus were published in the spring of 1959, the fall of 1959, and the summer of 1960, respectively. Exodus later became The Judson Review, edited by Rev. Al Carmines and Don Katzman. Volume I of The Judson Review was published in 1963 and included the poetry of Jackson Mac Low, Diane Wakoski, and Joel Oppenheimer.
In 1961, the Judson Poet's Theater was founded by Robert Nichols and Chuck Gordone, the Pulitzer Prize-winning playwright and a "free-wheeling" Sunday-school teacher at the church. The Judson Poet's Theater laid the foundation for "off off" Broadway theater, by producing plays by Rosalyn Drexler, Chuck Gordone, Maria Irene Fornes, Robert Nichols, Sam Shepard, and Lanford Wilson. In 1967, Rev. Al Carmines restructured the group and renamed it the Judson Musical Theater. The Judson Musical Theater produced musical theater performances throughout the late 1960's and the 1970's.
The Judson Dance Theater, which began in 1962, provided a venue for dancers and choreographers such as Trisha Brown, Lucinda Childs, Steve Paxton, David Gordon, and Yvonne Rainer to create and show their work. Among others, these dancers and choreographers shaped dance history by creating post-modern dance, the first avant-garde movement in dance theater since the modern dance of the 1930's and 1940's. Judson Dance Theater was founded by a group of young choreographers who had taken Robert Dunn's choreography course at the Merce Cunningham studio from 1960-1962. These choreographers decided to present a concert of work they had created during the Dunn course. Judson Memorial Church welcomed the group and provided space for rehearsal and performance. A Concert of Dance #1, open to the public and free of charge, was presented at Judson Memorial Church on July 6, 1962. This concert proved to be the beginning of the evolution of post-modern dance.
In the 1970's, the Judson Memorial Church hosted various art shows and multi-media events. Most notable among these multi-media events was the People's Flag Show of November 1970, a six-day exhibition of painting and sculpture on the theme of the American flag. The exhibit and the accompanying symposium, featuring speeches by Abbie Hoffman and Kate Millet, attracted widespread attention from the public, the press, and the police. During the final days of the exhibit, three of the contributing artists were arrested, Rev. Howard Moody was served with a summons, and the District Attorney closed the exhibit on charges of desecration of the American flag.
In the 1980's, the Judson Memorial Church sponsored various political theater performances, such as those by the Vermont-based Bread and Puppet Theater. These performances included Insurrection Opera and Oratorio, performed in February and March of 1984. In this performance, the Bread and Puppet Theater, under the direction of founder, Peter Schumann, used opera and the company's now signature oversized puppets to convey an anti-nuclear message.
The Judson Memorial Church celebrated its Centennial in 1990 with performances and symposia involving many of the artists who had been involved with the arts ministry in the 1960's and 1970's. The Judson Memorial Church continues its support of the arts and its social outreach to the community today. Among the church's present day arts-related activities is a free dance concert series coordinated by the dance organization, Movement Research, and held at the Judson Memorial Church on Monday evenings.
Scope and Contents
The Judson Memorial Church Oral History Archive contains oral history interviews and related documents concerning 21 prominent individuals associated with the Judson Memorial Church. The work was conducted by New York University graduate students in Professor Rachel Bernstein's Fall 2008 Oral History Class. The materials include administrative documents, student papers and presentations, and digital audio files of the oral history interviews.
The oral history interviewees were selected by the Judson Church Oral History Committee and Judson historian Ed Powers. The interviewees include political and social activists, artists, Judson Memorial Church clergy, and congregation members. The interviews cover a wide range of topics but focus primarily on the lives of the interviewees and the social, political, artistic, and religious activities of the Judson Church, with emphasis on the period of 1950 through the 1970s.
The original individuals interviewed include:
Bebe Anderson
Holly Bean
Reathel Bean
Keen Berger
Malcolm Goldstein
Grace Goodman
Peggy Halsey
Sue Harwig
Rose James
Harry Koutoukas
Arthur Levin
Mary Meyer
Howard Moody
Maxine Philips
Anna Lou Pickett
Tom Roderick
Tamara Rowe
Carolee Schneemann
Steve Studnicka
Elaine Summers
Rachel Tenney
Bethene Trexel
In 2018, an additional 11 oral history digital audio recordings were added to the existing collection. These interviews were conducted by Joanna Steinburg, one of Bernstein's former students on the oral history project. The 2010 interviews were primarily with artists in the Judson Dance Theater (including Steve Paxton and Yvonne Rainer), as well as congregants who had been part of the Judson Poets Theater. These interviews cover new ground, exploring the social context of the church, and recording the artists' reflections as they look back on their involvement at Judson 50 years later.
Agreements.; Oral history.; Artists. -- New York (State) -- New York. -- 20th century; Artists and community -- New York (State) -- New York; Interviews.; Steinberg, Joanna; Judson Poet's Theater; Trexel, Bethene; Roderick, Tom; Judson Dance Theater; Tenney, Rachel; Judson Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Studnicka, Steve; Anderson, Bebe; Berger, Keen; Bean, Holly; Bean, Reathel; Phillips, Maxine; Pickett, Anna Lou; Rowe, Tamara; Schneemann, Carolee, 1939-2019; Goldstein, Malcolm, 1936-; Moody, Howard, 1921-2012; Meyer, Mary; Levin, Arthur; Koutoukas, Harry; James, Rose; Harwig, Peggy; Halsey, Peggy; Goodman, Grace Ann; Rainer, Yvonne, 1934-; Paxton, Steve; Vaughan, David, 1924-2017; Passloff, Aileen; Summers, Elaine, 1925-2014; Guilliatt, Lee
- Series I: Administrative Papers, 2008; .25 Linear Feet in 2 file folders.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains general administrative forms collected during the oral history projects. The series includes a list of interviewees, student topics, interview agreements, Oral History Indices, interview worksheets, and partial transcripts for some of the interviews conducted.
  Arrangement
  The forms are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the interviewee.
  - Administrative Papers 1 of 2, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Papers 2 of 2, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Student-Produced Materials, 2008; 1.5 Linear Feet 1 manuscript box, 1 record carton, 1 file folder.
  This series contains materials produced by the students conducting the oral history interviews. These materials include fieldwork analysis papers that place the subjects of the interviews within a historical context, presentations that utilize the oral history information in a variety of public history projects, and digital files of the presentations.
  Papers and presentations in this series are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the students.
  - Subseries A: Fieldwork Analysis Papers, Fall 2008; 1 Folder
    - Fieldwork Analysis Papers, Fall 2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries B: Student Presentations, Fall 2008; 11 folders
    - "Something in the Air": Civil Rights, Women's Rights, and Activism in the 1960s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Life History of Ms. Rose James, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - History in Layers, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Judson Memorial Church: You Are Here, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Voices of New York 1950-1970, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Avant-Garde Theater -- Greenwich Village -- 1960s and 70s, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Judson Memorial Church: "It's All in the Timing": The Tenure of Reverend Howard Moody 1956-1992, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Judson Memorial Church and the Reproductive Rights Movement, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "A Sanctuary for Artistic Expression": Judson Dance Theater 1962-1966, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Voices of Judson Memorial Church: "Creating Community Across Generations", 2008 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Subseries C: Student Presentations CDs/DVDs, Fall 2008; 1 archive box, 11 folders.
    - Women and Social Movements, Elizabeth Banks, Ashley Welch, 12/17/08, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 1, Disk ID: 232.0035)
    - Documents and Images for History in Layers Exhibit, Keara Duggan, 18 December 2008, Oral History-NYU, Fall 2008 (Box 2, Folder 2, Disk ID: 232.0036)
    - Audio Clips, History in Layers Exhibit, Keara Duggan, Fall 2008 Oral History Course, Created 11 Dec. 2008 (Box 2, Folder 3, Disk ID: 232.0037)
    - Voices of New York 1950-1970, Blog and Attachments for Archives, Adina Langer, 12/13/08, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 4, Disk ID: 232.0038)
    - Walking Tour of the Avant-Garde Theaters, by Kaitlyn Medley, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 5, Disk ID: 232.0039)
    - Howard Moody, Oral History, Public History Exhibit, PowerPoint, Stacey Satchell, Fall Semester 2008 (Box 2, Folder 6, Disk ID: 232.0040)
    - Judson Memorial Church and the Reproductive Rights Movement, http://voicesofjudson.blogspot.com, Breanne Scanlon, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 7, Disk ID: 232.0041)
    - Audio Clips Used on http://voicesofjudson.blogspot.com, Howard Moody, Anna Lou Pickett, Mary Meyer, Breanne Scanlon, NYU Fall '08, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 8, Disk ID: 232.0042)
    - Philip Corner's "On Tape from the Judson Years", 2008 (Box 2, Folder 9, Disk ID: 232.0043)
    - Final Project on Judson Dance Theater (PowerPoint), Joanna Steinberg, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 10, Disk ID: 232.0044)
    - Voices of Judson Memorial Church - Final Project, Final PowerPoint, Oral History Audio Clips, Laura Zeccardi 12/15/08, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 11, Disk ID: 232.0045)
- Series III: Oral History Interview Audio Discs, 2008
  This series contains digital audio discs of the complete interviews.
  - Subseries A: Audio - Access Copies, 2008
    - Bebe Anderson Oral History, Interviewed by Ashley Welch, 12/9/2008, ID: 232.0047 (Case 232.0047)
      General Note
      Bebe Anderson Oral History December 9, 2008
      Interviewed by Ashley Welch
      Disc 1 of 1 (61 minutes)
      Ordinary People, Extraordinary Lives Oral History Project
      Track 1: Childhood in California
      Track 2: Family, Parents
      Track 3: Education
      Track 4: Move to New York City
      Track 5: Legal Career
      Track 6: Judson Memorial Church
      Track 7: Activist?
      Track 8: religion and Ethics
      Track 9: Significant Historical Events
    - Holly Bean Oral History Parts I & II, Interviewed by Elizabeth Banks, 11/18/2008, ID: 232.0049, ID: 232.0051 (Case 232.0049, Case 232.0051)
      Holly Bean Oral History
      November 18, 2008
      Interviewed by Elizabeth Banks
      Disc 1 of 1 (100 minutes)
      Judson Memorial Church Oral History Project
      Disc 1 of 1 (100 Minutes)
      Track 1: Childhood - Moving Around and Family
      Track 2: Attitudes Toward Race and Gender at Home
      Track 3: Early Interest in Religion, Diversity
      Track 4: Part of the Baby Boom Generation
      Track 5: College and Its Meaning for a Woman
      Track 6: New York, Work and Family
      Track 7: Judson, Programs and Philosophy
      Track 8: Pursuing a Career as a Minister
      Track 9: Fighting Fear and Societal Pressures for a Career
      Track 10: Final Reflections
    - Reathel Bean Oral History Parts I & II, Interviewed by Kait Medley, 10/10/2008, ID: 232.0053, ID: 232.0055 (Case 232.0053, Case 232.0055)
      Reathel Bean Oral History
      October 10, 2008
      Interviewed by Kait Medley
      Disc 1 of 1 (87 minutes)
      Track 1: Childhood in Missouri
      Track 2: Junior High and High School
      Track 3: College and Religious Background
      Track 4: Civil Rights Activities
      Track 5: Judson Memorial Church and Acting in the 1960s
      Track 6: Adult Life
    - Keen Berger Oral History Parts I & II, Interviewed by Elizabeth Banks, 10/10/2008, ID: 232.0057, ID: 232.0059 (Case 232.0057, Case 232.0059)
      Keen Berger Oral History
      Disc 1 of 1 (118 minutes)
      Track 1: Childhood and Upbringing
      Track 2: College
      Track 3: Involvement in Civil Rights
      Track 4: New York and Judson Church
      Track 5: Marriage and Family Life
      Track 6: Teaching
      Track 7: Politics on a Professional Level
      Track 8: Reflections on Social Change
      Track 9: Writing
      Track 10: Conclusions
    - Malcolm Goldstein Oral History Parts I & II, Interviewed by Joanna Steinberg, 10/16/2008, ID: 232.0061, ID: 232.0063 (Case 232.0061, Case 232.0063)
      Malcolm Goldstein Oral History
      October 16, 2008
      Interviewed by Joanna Steinberg
      Judson Church Project
      Disc 1 of 7 (2 hours)
      Track 1: Childhood in Brooklyn and Queens, family (parents and brother), religion, community, edication (in school and in music), early ambitions and experiences with violin, composition, music theory
      Track 2: Music Education: formal training vs. instruction in composition and music theory. Instruction by Antonio Miranda
      Break -- Issue with recording device
      Track 3: Introduction and contributions to Judson Dance Theater: reflections on collaboration and improvisation and the use of the body.
      Track 4: Thoughts on the politics of improvisation (Sounding the Full Circle); conceptual art in relation to politics; other aspects of career outside of Judson in 1960s (Tone Roads Ensemble)
      Track 5: Art that "creates an experience" and "develops awareness;" textured art, improvisation, and trust
      Track 6: Working with Elaine Summers at Judson Church on "Fantastic Gardens"
      Track 7: Art at Judson Church; mentions Al Carmines and Rev. Howard Moody; Greenwich Village (1960s); teaching positions; other projects; political issues
      Track 8: Family (children); orchestra in Puerto Rico and Central America; Vermont; community
      Track 9: Tone Roads Ensemble; recent projects and continual interaction and collaborations with friends; residency in Canada
      Track 10: Sons; current projects; writing, graphic work, poetry; personal archives; conclusion
    - Grace Goodman Oral History Parts I & II, Interviewed by Brigid Harmon, 10/16/2008, ID: 232.0065, ID: 232.0067 (Case 232.0065, Case 232.0067)
    - Peggy Halsey Oral History Parts I & II, Interviewed by Ashley Welch, 10/20/2008, ID: 232.0069, ID: 232.0071 (Case 232.0069, Case 232.0071)
      Peggy Halsey Oral History
      October 20, 2008
      Disc 1 of 1 (122 minutes)
      Track 1: Moving to New York City
      Track 2: Childhood in Florida
      Track 3: Judson Church
      Track 5: Career-Board of Global Ministries
      Track 6: Judson Work
      Track 7: Memories of father
      Track 8: Memories of mother, siblings
      Track 9: College
      Track 10: Activism in Civil Rights Movement
      Track 11: High School
      Track 12: September 11th
      Track 13: Painting, hobby
    - Sue Harwig Oral History Part One, Interviewed by Adina Langer, 10/17/2008, ID: 232.0073 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 232.0073)
      Sue Harwig, CD1 Backup, Interview 10/17/08, Adina Langer, 55:17, 1/3
    - Sue Harwig Oral History Part Two, Interviewed by Adina Langer, 10/17/2008, ID: 232.0075 (Case 232.0075)
      Sue Harwig, CD2 Backup, Interviewed by Adina Langer, 10/17/08, 25:47, 2/3
    - Sue Harwig Oral History Part Three, Interviewed by Adina Langer, 10/17/2008, ID: 232.0077 (Case 232.0077)
      Sue Harwig, CD3 Backup, Interviewed by Adina Langer, 10/17/08, 44:13, 3/3
    - Rose James Oral History Part One, 10/17/2008, ID: 232.0079 (Case 232.0079)
    - Rose James Oral History Part Two, 11/10/2008, ID: 232.0081 (Case 232.0081)
    - Harry Koutoukas Oral History, Interviewed by Kait Medley, 11/11/2008, ID: 232.0083 (Case 232.0083)
      Harry Koutoukas Oral History
      November 11, 2008
      Disc 1 of 1 (71 minutes)
      Ordinary People, Extraordinary lives Oral History Project
      Track 1: First experiences with avant-garde theater
      Track 2: Experience with Judson
      Track 3: Ellen Stewart and La Mama
      Track 4: Involvement with Stonewall
      Track 5: Family Life
      Track 6: The end of avant-garde
    - Arthur Levin Oral History Part One, Interviewed by Stacey Satchell, 11/24/2008, ID: 232.0085 (Case 232.0085)
      Arthur Levin Oral History (part 2)
      November 24, 2008
      Interviewed by Stacey Satchell
      Disc 1 of 2 (71 minutes total)
      Track 1: Early Life, Upper West Side, New York
      Track 2: Village Independent Democrats, met Moody
      Track 3: Early involvement with Judson, runaways
      Track 4: After runaway program, Judson staff
      Track 5: Beginnings of involvement in health care
      Track 6: Abortion programs, CCS/CRASH
      Track 7: Development of Center for Medical Consumers
      Track 8: More public health experiences
      Track 9: Discussion of Judson environment
      Track 10: Political involvement
    - Arthur Levin Oral History Part Two, Interviewed by Stacey Satchell, 11/24/2008, ID: 232.0087 (Case 232.0087)
      Arthur Levin Oral History (Part 2)
      Disc 2 of 2 (71 minutes total)
      Track 11: Military service experience
      Track 12: Late 1960s activism
      Track 13: AIDS task force
      Track 14: Prositution project
      Track 15: Late political involvement, disillusioned
      Track 16: Appreciation of Judson
      Track 17: Brainstorming youth programs, early
    - Mary Meyer Oral History Part One, Interviewed by Breanne Scanlon, 10/26/2008, ID: 232.0089 (Case 232.0089)
    - Mary Meyer Oral History Part Two, Interviewed by Breanne Scanlon, 10/26/2008, ID: 232.0091 (Case 232.0091)
    - Howard Moody Oral History Part One, Disc One, Interviewed by Stacey Satchell, 10/15/2008, ID: 232.0093 (Case 232.0093)
      Howard Moody Oral History (Part 1)
      October 15, 2008
      Disc 1 of 2(77:37 minutes)
      Track 1: Childhood, early life
      Track 2: Santa Barbara (post-WWII)